when we create something
we often leave traces of our internal
decisions
i like finding patterns in mind and
formalizing them into rule sets
this way i can translate my creative
intuition into algorithms
and have the computer amplify my process
and co-create with me
but this takes time and expertise
rendering it inaccessible to many
i don't think it should be that way i
believe we can minimize the gap
between expressing creative intent and
realizing it
and i believe we can do it with
algorithms that learn from the user's
examples
enabling more people to amplify their
work with personal tools
which they create by simply expressing
themselves in their creative media and
today we will have a look at an instance
of such an algorithm
that infers rules from a user example of
object placements
welcome to place like i do example based
procedural placements in a dialect
system
my name is anastasio para and i'm a
procedural artist at embark studios
so you might be wondering what is
example-based procedural placement
when creating a scene probably the most
common way of doing it would be placing
each asset by hand
however that quickly becomes tedious
especially for larger scenes
and any future modification will have to
be carried out by hand too
thus the creative iteration loop of how
fast we can explore new ideas and
iterate on existing ones
becomes stifled by execution time it
takes for each iteration
another way would be to write a small
procedural algorithm to have the
computer do the tedious work for us
however writing an algorithm requires
translating creative intent
into a logic based code which is time
consuming and poses a knowledge barrier
for many
and it also forces us to interrupt our
creative loop to solve the idea to code
translation problem
with example-based placement we would
like to automate this process
thus reinforcing our creative loop
without interrupting it
and we do so by asking the user to
provide an example of what they want
which we automatically analyze and break
down into rules
and with this rules we can synthesize
new similar looking
content and there are many ways how one
can design an interaction with
example-based placement algorithm
so i'd like to give you a peek into one
of our latest experiments
where we used example based placement as
a vehicle to explore a feeling of
co-creation with a procedural system
in a dialogue-like interaction in our
experiment
we embodied the example-based procedural
placement algorithm
into this little creature whom we named
kittus ketus tries to assist you
by mimicking your placements it analyzes
the neighborhood of objects you place
and find similar looking locations in
the level so if you place grass near a
tree and a rock
kitties will place a new grass near
another tree in a rock using your
previous placement as an example
and by going back and forth between you
and quitus you end up co-creating a
small scene together
and sometimes kiddos cannot find a
perfect match to your placement
but sets when it becomes interesting as
it has to improvise
and this i place you place interaction
was a part of slightly bigger experience
a project called kitty wake where you
are on a small planet
and together with multiple kitty you
populate it with assets and give it a
bit of life
this is how kitty wake looks like this
is a recording of me playing a session
in this demo we had a slightly different
interaction to the previous test you've
seen
here you have to copy an existing object
to place a new one
and by positioning objects in specific
patterns you unlock new objects
sort of progressive asset discovery and
some objects interact with each other if
located nearby
to introduce a second order effect to
your and kitty placements
overall kit awake was a very educational
experience for us
we released it internally on our own
tech stack written in rust
we got a bunch of awesome user feedback
for example embodying the algorithm into
a personified creature
established an emotional connection and
it was a lot of fun observing people
play with kitty
surfacing such questions as what is the
ideal relationship with kitty
are they just your tools like your
slaves obeying blindly
or more like paths that can have a
mischievous mind of their own
at the same time kitty wake evoked a
more micro management mode than we
intended
due to kitty and users sharing the same
action space of direct placements
one can probably do a separate purely ux
dedicated talk about kitty wake
but this presentation is more about how
kitty work
on the inside so we're gonna talk about
a lot of fairly technical things that
comprise the kitty brain
such as concept of possibility space
sampling that space with markov chain
monte carlo
defining similarity metric for spatial
arrangements of objects
and also have a brief introduction to
optimal transport and versus 10 distance
if those are the things you've never
heard about don't panic
my main goal is to give you an intuition
about these algorithms and hopefully
inspire you to use some of them in your
own work
so let's start our deep dive by
introducing you to kitus bob and kittus
mary
whose placements we will use as an
example bob and mary like being close to
each other
but not too close they do like their
personal space
and being too far apart is also not
great and makes them sad
one can say they have a very functional
relationship meaning we can express
mary's and bob's happiness as a function
of their proximity to one another
the relationship can be captured with a
graph like this one where the bottom
axis is a distance between bob and mary
and the upper axis is how happy they are
with each of those placements
now suppose bob and mary are moving into
a new town
it's a lovely one-dimensional street
with an exquisite selection of
one-dimensional locations to choose from
and we are faced with the task of
finding new home for bob and mary
that would make them happy according to
their happiness function which says that
they are most happy when they are about
1 meter apart
as instead of reasoning about bob and
mary in world space
let's separate mary's and bob's location
into their own axis
thus any configuration of bob and mary
can now be expressed as a point in this
new two-dimensional space
for example this point with a coordinate
4 and 6 simply represents that mary is
on coordinate 4
and bob on coordinates 6. and now we can
very easily explore
all possible bob mary placements just by
moving around
in this new two-dimensional space which
we will call possibility space
since it describes all possible bob
merry configurations
note how every configuration corresponds
to a certain value in the score function
indicated by the moving yellow dot we
can evaluate that score for every point
in the possibility space
and visually see where good bulk memory
configurations
tend to form in general we are
interested in the regions of high scores
indicated by yellow dots in the
possibility space and as you can see
there are a lot of good solutions
and we can pick any of them to generate
the final placement
that would make bob and mary happy we
can also change the initial score
function and see how regions of good
solutions change as well
for example if we introduce bimodality
to our score function
making bob and mary either wanting to be
super close or
five meters away from each other that is
also reflected in our possibility space
as well as in the final solutions we
present in the world
one can say that the regions of good
solutions are shaped by mary's and bob's
score function
which i find conceptually very
interesting if you think of this
function
as a sort of soft rule or condition that
we are trying to meet
and possibility space represents all
possible outputs of our algorithm
meaning that the rules are not defined
explicitly in code but rather are
parameters of our algorithm
in turn that means that with the same
piece of code we can generate
all kinds of bobbin memory placement
configurations just by changing the
score function
but so far we've only talked about 2kt
meaning our possibility space was
defined by only two parameters
making it two-dimensional and easy to
visualize and talk about
but suppose mary's distant cousin
decides to also move in
well now when reasoning about good
solutions we need to take his position
into account
two making our possibility space
three-dimensional
now imagine the whole family decides to
move in and they all have special
requests such as
someone wants to live close to mandy but
others have a rivalry with
bill and want to be as far away as
possible visualizing that becomes tricky
if we have 60 kitty to place that would
be a 60 dimensional space
that is if kitty's positions are
one-dimensional with three dimensions
our overall dimensionality blows up to
and it's not just a problem of
visualization our possibility space
grows
exponentially as we add more dimensions
but the regions of good solutions shrink
as we add more constraints such as
making each kitty happy with its
placements it's much easier to do that
for 2kt rather than 60.
in numerical analysis and machine
learning this problem is called the
curse of dimensionality
as our possibility space becomes sparse
meaning it's big and filled mostly with
bad solutions
finding good ones becomes non-trivial
especially if we'd like to do that in
interactive times
and generally the more dimensions you
have the more dark and full of terrors
your search space is
so what do we do let's consider an
imaginary
many dimensional possibility space for
the purpose of making an example
i'm going to portray it in two
dimensions but you can imagine that
moving from one point of the space to
another
involves tweaking dozens of parameters
so just as before every point is
associated with some kind of score
and sure right now we see exactly where
great scores are
but suppose the space is just so big
that we
cannot physically visit every single
point
like i did to make this visualization we
need to deploy
some kind of search strategy and one way
of doing it
is searching at random we just traverse
the space by randomly choosing direction
every single step but it is a very
unreliable search strategy
since we are never guaranteed that
anything reasonable will come out of it
in a given budget of
say 500 steps we can be lucky and
stumble upon something great
but chances of that happening
consistently are very small
so we can perhaps guide this randomness
by asking it to only accept a step in a
new direction
if the score would become better this
search strategy is called greedy
and it sounds good on paper since it
does consistently find
ok solutions however it tends to get
stuck
in local maxima meaning it finds an okay
solution surrounded by bad solutions
so no matter what direction it will try
it will always be worse
so it will just never set out to explore
again and then we have markov chain
monte carlo
short mcmc which i like to think about
as
something in between greedy and random
since mcmc
just like greedy always accepts a new
step if it's better
however if this step is worse unlike
greedy which just discards it
mcmc has a chance of accepting it a
chance
inversely proportional to how much worse
this new score is
thus mcmc will gravitate towards good
scores but not get stuck in local maxima
and with enough number of steps we can
be sure it will find a good solution
but doesn't it all sound like a lot of
work
wouldn't we like take forever to find
the best solution in a real scenario
well the reality is that we are not
interested
in the best solution we are interested
in a good enough solution that we can
find in
reasonable time and when this time
becomes real time
that's when it starts feeling magical in
fact we would prefer finding
a variety of good answers opposed to a
single best answer
because this way we can present the user
with a variety of alternatives
example of which we will see later
okay so we know we're going to be
comparing a lot of different placement
configurations with one another
you can say one of the core questions of
our search strategy
is which one is better and by how much
because if it's better we accept it and
if it's worse we need to know by how
much
so we can use this ratio as a
probability of accepting or rejecting it
and with kitty comparing one kitty
placement to another was
pretty simple because a score was
defined by a function
that was given to us all we had to do is
plug in the distance between bob and
mary
and see what value our function spits
out and then just use it for comparisons
for example here we can easily say that
the placement on the right
is 10 times better than the placement on
the left
but what do we do if we're not given a
score function
but just an example of how we want our
placements to look like
suddenly the question which one is
better a or b in this case
becomes rather ambiguous we can probably
pick which one is better
based on some kind of internal judgment
but how do we say by how much
it's better we need a numerical way of
expressing
how similar one spatial object
arrangement is to another
so it has to be some kind of function
that takes our example and compares it
to another object arrangement
we don't know what it is yet but let's
just have a closer look at a and b
maybe we can find a pattern for example
we can notice that
a is practically the same as our example
except for the rock and the tree being
swapped places
so if we just move them around then a
would be identical to the example and we
can
probably mutate b to be identical to
example as well
and indeed with just few more steps we
can
but hey that sounds like a procedure we
can use to judge similarity
if we count how many steps we performed
to make a and b
look like the example we can see that a
took us fewer steps than b
so we are starting to get numbers that
reflect our intuition about similarity
and if we invert the numbers of steps we
get
something that is very close to what we
think of as similarity
and now we can use these numbers to
compute the arrangement a
is twice as good as arrangement b
and this was one of our key observations
when working on example-based placement
that similarity of two arrangements x
and y can be expressed
in terms of minimum number of steps it
takes to morph
x into y and it's important that it's a
minimum number of steps
because we can have many possible ways
of how to morph x and y
and if we choose a different one every
time well that would make our similarity
symmetric quite unreliable
and so happens that we are in a great
luck because this formulation sounds a
lot like a mathematical field called
optimal transport so here's a small
sketch to introduce you to what optimal
transport is about
imagine two mathematicians lying on a
beach it's lovely sunset
smooth silky sand and then one of them
says
hey why don't we build a sand castle
from the sand on this beach
and of course being a practical
mathematician the other one is
the first thing they say is but how much
work would it take to move the scent
from its original shape into the shape
of a castle
and the other mathematician will reply
trivial my friend
the work we would need to do is
proportional to the total distance
travelled by each grain of sand we move
we can minimize this work with this
transport plan
and the transfer plan just tells us how
much stuff we need to move from one
location
to another how much sand we need to move
from the left heel of the beach
to make the castle tower and usually we
are interested in finding the optimal
plan that would minimize the work
one would need to do so the other
mathematician would exclaim
the vassestein distance between this
beach and a sandcastle
is not as big as i thought translated to
human english that would mean
it's not as much work as i thought it
would be
what's this time distance even though it
sounds very fancy
it's just a minimum amount of work one
would need to
in this case move the scent into the
shape of a castle
and the exciting part is that we do not
need to find the optimal transport plan
to calculate the vassa's time distance
if we are in one dimension since one d
was stein has a very neat closed form
solution which is very fast and easy to
calculate
all we need to do is take cumulative
distribution function or
cdf of the castle and the beach which is
a function whose value at a particular
x is the sum of all the preceding axis
values
so it's literally showing an
accumulation of our function values
and to compute vasa style we just need
to find an area
between the cdfs of the castle and the
beach which in discrete case
such as a histogram becomes simply a bin
wise absolute difference
unfortunately this trick doesn't work
for more dimensions
but soon you will see just how much we
can do with that single dimension
so returning to the original question we
had of which object arrangement is
better and by how much
we can now use our new similarity metric
that is defined in terms of business
time distance
so the biggest advances then distance is
meaning it takes more work for us to
morph something to look like the example
the lower our similarity and score are
and this allows us to numerically
compare
different object arrangements based on
the user's example
so far we have been comparing the whole
example arrangement
unfortunately with such a formulation we
would only have a good score
if we make a perfect copy if we just
deviate a little
from the example our similarity function
will become instantly lower
scared to think what would happen if we
have different number of objects like
what do we do then
this highlights a fundamental issue we
do not want to generate something it is
exactly like the example
instead we would like to infer the rules
of the example's placements
to do so we assume that user's placement
is a product of object neighborhood
rules
interacting with each other and that
interaction is the core that makes one's
example
look like itself and if we capture those
we can synthesize different but similar
looking arrangements
and we do it by asking each synthesized
object what is your neighborhood
then we search for the most similar
neighborhood that exists in the example
and it might so happen there is no
perfect match but that would not be a
problem because we can just use the same
vassa's time-based similarity metric
we've been using before which would
return as a score
describing how similar is the
synthesized object neighborhood
to this neighborhood from the example
and we can repeat this process for every
object
and then take a product of all
individual object scores to calculate
the final score for the synthesized
arrangement
i like to think of it as if every object
has a preference
like the house wants to be close to the
grass but far away from the tree
but the cross wants to be close to the
tree and so on and then the final score
represents
how happy is each object with this
neighborhood
so by moving the object around we change
how happy the object
and affected neighbors are with their
new neighborhoods
and we use mcmc to guide this iterative
process
and find such a configuration of
placements that would satisfy everyone
for example here the example is to have
a rock and a tree close together
and grass scattered around and of course
if we change the example
like saying no now we want two trees
close to each other and draw close to
the grass but the grass can also be just
separate from both the rock and the tree
our solutions change as well and we can
restart the possibility space search to
find novel solutions
thus we can generate a whole variety of
placements that satisfy the example
there is however a catch all of our
neighborhoods are 2d
but remember our sketch about
weissestein distance only one
devastating has a neat closed form
solution
the trick we used for calculating it
just wouldn't work for 2d
we started with an approach used in
prior work to compress
our 2d neighborhood into a 1d
representation by considering only the
distances to our neighbors instead of
their relative to depositions
and often the distance information is
enough to represent the example
and having a time based similarity
metric was helping in tone as well
however in some cases it was just still
problematic
like in this example where we wanted to
build a road with zakirus
and kit is just completely fails
to continue our example and that's
something that just doesn't correspond
to our intuition
so yeah so why is this happening when we
compress our neighborhood into purely
distances
will lose angle information kiddos can
no longer see the difference between a
rock on the left versus a rock on the
right
often two very different neighborhoods
would look exactly the same in kittus's
eyes
like in this example the left
neighborhood has a clear directionality
to it
whereas the right one doesn't but
because the distances of
rocks to the center of the neighborhood
are the same those neighborhoods are
perceived as equivalent
and the question of how to combat this
stumbled me during our first prototype
and was just like sitting at the back of
my mind for a couple of months until
by coincidence at the same time both my
colleague thomas zahoiak and smart
people on the twitter
suggested sliced westerstein so what
is sliced western imagine this is a
neighborhood we are trying to compare to
some other neighborhood we literally
slice through this neighborhood
in this case with three lines s1 s2
and s3 and we project the whole
neighborhood onto each of those slices
thus approximating the depositions of
our neighborhood
with multiple 1d projections
and to compare with another neighborhood
we compare each slice with a
corresponding slice from another
neighborhood
and then we can calculate the nice and
easy one d westerstein for each of those
pair of slices
and by summing this wassensteins we have
computed sliced vases stein
which is approximately proportional to
the true vasa stein
but that kind of approximation is
completely okay for us because we are
only interested in relative comparisons
anyway not the true values
and probably the best part about slide
vases time is that it's still fast to
compute
in fact we can control exactly the speed
by changing the number of slices
thus trading of approximation accuracy
and now
ketus can build rows with us
and note how by placing the rock
kind of to the curvature to the right
the ketus is also continuing the road to
the right
and when i place grass on the right side
of the road he just does
the same and if i place it on the left
side he just also places on the left and
the same would happen with trees
thus we ended up co-creating a small
scene together goodkittus
so to summarize we've talked about our
experimental project kittywake where we
set out to explore a feeling of
co-creation with an example-based
placement algorithm
then we dive deep into possibility space
which represents
all possible outputs of our algorithm
and when the space becomes too big
we need to deploy search strategy such
as markov chain monte carlo
however for mcmc to work we need a way
to score every new proposed arrangement
thus we've covered a way to numerically
express similarity between two spatial
arrangements of objects
and it's important to note that this
metric is not always equivalent to how
humans perceive patterns
but it is a convenient assumption next
we talked about how optimal transport
can help us to formulate our similarity
metric
and quickly compute it in one dimension
then we talked about breaking down the
example into neighborhood interactions
to prevent the algorithm from creating
an exact copy of the example
and instead synthesize different but
similar looking arrangements
then we showed how to compare to the
neighborhoods when you only have one
divestine
either by only considering distances to
objects or using sliced basistine
and finally we've shown how it all comes
together into kitty
assisting use placements and co-creating
a small scene together
our example-based placement is still
work in progress there are a ton of
things we'd like to try out such as
negative examples remixing and sharing
examples
creating bigger scenes and also
exploring different interaction models
and before we wrap up i'd like to take a
moment to admire the network of
interconnected research and ideas that
allowed us to build the example-based
placement algorithm
that for example the very first
example-based arrangement paper
was inspired by texture synthesis and
procedural content generation
and later the idea was expanded with the
knowledge from statistical analysis
and even our main contribution the
similarity metric for object
arrangements
is again bridging ideas from another
field such as optimal transport
i would also like to take a moment to
give a shout out to thomas sahovic whose
ideas help and feedback
were a big part of making the algorithm
and i would also like to thank all the
people who brought kittywig to life
as well as embark for his amazing brew
of so many talented people
super passionate culture and many fun
and hard problems to tackle with an
overarching goal
i strongly believe in here is a list of
references of all the papers
if you're interested to dig deeper and i
also included the inspirations i used
for making the art in this presentation
and one last thing when it comes to
content creation
we as a games industry are very familiar
with making content
manually we're getting better at
designing rules to automate making
content
also known as proceduralism and the next
step in my opinion
is to go further and ask how we can go
directly from creative intent to content
by interpreting that intent and
extracting the relevant rules that would
create the content
and hopefully by doing so we can also
allow more people to experience the joy
of game creation
together with us and that would be it
thank you so much for listening and if
this area of co-creation
enabling others to create is something
that resonates with you
either from technical perspective or ux
and design perspective
give us a shout we'd love to hear from
you thank you